Vinay Singh

Research Scholar

- O Kanpur, Uttar Pradesh, 208013
- + 91 9560800827
- ✓ vs2255068@gmail.com

- in https://www.linkedin.com/in/vinaysingh-030098125
- https://zety.com/profile/vinay-singh/418

Meticulous and analytical Researcher with 4 years of educational and hands-on experience in Physics. Adaptive team player with in-depth knowledge of data collection, confidential document control and problem-solving. Highly motivated individual committed to hard work and intensive analysis. Flexible and polished Senior Research Associate promoting well-developed skills in

- C++, Scilab, Matlab, Python, Fortran
- Origin Pro, ROOT, GEANT4, SRIM, KATEX, JSX Generator
- Machine Learning, Data Science



Skills

- Data analysis
- Research program planning
- Microsoft Excel proficiency
- Quantitative analysis
- Electron microscopes
- Spectroscopy
- Team Building
- Research implementation
- Deep-dive data analysis
- Quantum Optics



Work History

2020-08 - Current

Researcher

IIT Kanpur, Kanpur, Uttar Pradesh

- Performed research into study topics to increase knowledge and ability to provide valuable contributions.
- Collaborated with staff to develop and implement best practices and accomplished all team goals.
- Gathered and organized information for research purposes.
- Collaborated with team members to initiate best practices to achieve

2020-03 - 2021-07

2019-05 - 2021-07

2018-07 - 2020-01

2018-07 - 2020-07

organizational goals.

- Used Python to determine data-set correlations while initiating qualitative functions.
- Performed Quantum entanglement experiments and research and documented all findings.
- Directed students in performing and completing assigned tasks.
- Performed statistical, qualitative and quantitative analysis.

Subject Matter Expert

Six Red Marbles, Banglore, karnataka

- Collaborated with senior management and business line management to identify and prioritize new concepts for development and launch.
- Designed and prepared technical reports, studies and related documentation.
- Marked charts and graphs to record results and prepared and delivered presentations, training and briefings required by contract.

Research Intern

Karlsruhe Institute of Technology, Karlsruhe, Baden-Württemberg, Germany

- Dark Matter particle (WIMP) analysis using Simulation Technique in GEANT4, ROOT and SRIM Calculated Track Length, Energy Deposit and many other interaction Properties of WIMP particles with Palaeo Detectors, which are radically different from conventional detectors located inside deep underground Labs.
- Researched various subjects that were related to project and presented information to appropriate stakeholders.
- Attended meetings and presentations to learn more details about Dark Matter.
- Compiled data in reports and other documents using Overleaf, Online Latex editor.
- Collected, analyzed and reviewed experimental data for publication and presentation.
- Extensively used **Python** to compile experimental data.

Subject Matter Expert

Chegg, Mumbai, Maharashtra

- Documented client progress through case notes and documentation.
- Solved Physics related complex problems using Scilab



Education

Master of Physics: Physics

IIT Bombay, Delhi University - Powai, Maharashtra GPA: 8.94

- Received **Scholarship for Higher Education (SHE)** under the scheme, innovation in science pursuit for inspired research **(INSPIRE)** by department of science and technology by Government of India.
- Research Project: Direct Detection of WIMP Dark Matter under Prof. Vikram Rentala .In this Project we were searching for the best Crystal Material (like-

2015-07 - 2018-06

halite crystals) which can have measurable interaction with Dark Matter Candidates so that we can have a good support of **ACDM** (**Lambda cold dark matter**).

Bachelor of Science: Physics

Kirori Mal College - New Delhi CGPA - 8.55

• Received INSPIRE from Government of India.



Accomplishments

Entrance exam year AIR IIT JAM 2018 25 JEST 2018 26 GATE 2020 14 CSIR JRF 2020 65